Peter Blos PhD Papers Finding Aid
Oskar Diethelm Library
Peter Blos PhD Papers
1923 - 1997
1964 - 1990
This collection contains the papers of Peter Blos, who was one of the central figures in child and adolescent analysis. The collection has 9 series: Correspondence (1966-1995), Lectures (1949-1995, n.d.), Manuscripts (1966-1995, n.d.), Marta Grone Correspondence (1957-1964, n.d.), Case Seminars (1957-1963, n.d.), Miscellaneous (1950-1993, n.d.), Reprints (1935-1991), Photographs, and Certificates (1934-1988).
6.42 linear feet (14 boxes)
Blos, Peter
Oskar Diethelm Library DeWitt Wallace Institute of Psychiatry: History, Policy and the Arts Weill Cornell Medical College 525 East 68th Street, Box 140 New York, NY 10065
2000.0001
The Library of Congress Manuscript Division holds a small collection of papers donated by Peter Blos.
The Peter Blos Papers were donated by Mrs. Betsy Blos, the late widow to Peter Blos, in the year 2000. Approximately 350 books were donated along with the papers and have been cataloged and added to the library’s book collection.
Some materials in series V Case Seminars are restricted due to private health information. Restricted material has been removed and filed separately.
Peter Blos (1904-1997) was one of the central figures in child and adolescent analysis. Born in 1904 in Karlsruhe, Germany, he studied education at the University of Heidelberg and then obtained a PhD in biology from the University of Vienna. While in Vienna, Blos made the acquaintance of Anna Freud, who requested his help in creating a school for children undergoing analysis. The project was supported and encouraged by Evan Rosenfeld and Dorothy Burlingham, a Tiffany heir and friend of Anna Freud’s, and August Aichhorn, an Austrian educator and psychoanalyst. Burlingham’s children attended the school, along with children of other individuals prominent in the psychoanalytic field. Blos recruited an old friend, Erik Homburger Erikson (later a leading figure in psychoanalysis) to join him. The Experimental School, as it was called, employed psychoanalytic principles and encouraged the children to think for themselves.
Blos immigrated to the United States in 1934 to escape the rise of Nazism. He originally settled in New Orleans to teach at a private school, but then left for New York to continue his psychoanalytic training. While in New York, Blos became involved in a major study on adolescence. Blos worked with people from different professions during this time, including anthropologist Margaret Mead, pediatrician Benjamin Spock, and psychoanalyst Erik Erikson. He published his first book, The Adolescent Personality, in 1941.
Over the course of his career, Blos taught at the Jewish Board of Guardians, the New York Psychoanalytic Society, and the Columbia Psychoanalytic Center. On Adolescence, published in 1961, is his fourth book and the one that gave him national and international recognition. Blos died in 1997 in his country home in Holderness, New Hampshire at the age of 93.
Blos, Peter; Child analysis; Adolescent analysis; Psychoanalysis; Vienna (Austria); New York Psychoanalytic Institute; Freudian Society
This collection consists of correspondence, professional writing, drafts, notes, photographs, and other personal and professional materials dating from 1923-1997. The materials are primarily in English, but also include letters, manuscripts, and notes in German and Swedish. The papers are divided into nine series: Correspondence (1966-1995), Lectures (1949-1995, n.d.), Manuscripts (1966-1995, n.d.), Marta Grone Correspondence (1957-1964, n.d.), Case Seminars (1957-1963, n.d.), Miscellaneous (1950-1993, n.d.), Reprints (1935-1991), Photographs (1990-1994), and Certificates (1934-1988). There are oversized materials in the following series: Manuscripts, Reprints, Certificates, and Miscellaneous. These materials are stored together in oversize boxes 12 (legal size) and 13 (oversize flat box).
Correspondence: This series is organized in the order in which it was received. It contains Blos’ professional (and some personal) correspondence. Materials relate to writings, translations, lectures, paper requests, and appointments.
Lectures: This series, arranged by lecture or discussion, contains an assortment of papers read by Blos at lectures and symposiums. It also contains Blos’ notes from lectures, colloquiums, symposiums, and discussions.
Manuscripts: This series, arranged by manuscript title, consists of published works by Peter Blos and others. Some of these include “Freud and the Father Complex,” “Son and Father,” and “The Place of the Adolescent Process in the Analysis of the Adult.” In addition to the finished copies, the collection includes a number of oversized drafts pasted together on yellow lined paper and marked with handwritten edits. They are all housed in oversize box 12 and box 13 (folders 1-5). The content of this series is mostly in English with some of the drafts and finished manuscripts in German.
Marta Grone Blos Correspondence: This series is arranged in chronological order, preserving the groupings by which they were organized at the time of donation. The groupings are titled: “Pa’s Disease (sjukdom),” “Pa’s Letters (brev),” and “Elsa/Pa’s Letters (brev).” The letters in this series are written in Swedish and contain private correspondence between Marta Blos, Peter Blos’ first wife, and her family.
Case Seminars: This series has been maintained in its original order. Some materials are restricted due to private health information. The restricted folders have been removed and are housed separately.
Reprints: This series is arranged chronologically and contains reprints of articles and papers from journals, magazines, and newspapers, including works by Peter Blos and other authors. Some materials are oversized and stored in flat box 13, folders 6-7.
Certificates: This series has been arranged chronologically and includes various certificates, awards, commendations, and memberships. Some materials in this series are oversized and stored in flat box 12, folder 8.
Miscellaneous: This series includes book reviews, notes, personal journals, and other miscellany. Some materials are oversized and stored in flat box 13 folders 9-10.
Photographs: This series includes a photo album of buildings from Vienna, professional photographs taken in 1990, and photographic negatives.
- Correspondence, 1966 - 1995
  - Professional correspondence, 1966 - 1978 (Box 1)
  - Professional correspondence, 1985 - 1988 (Box 1)
  - Professional correspondence, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Professional correspondence, 1988 - 1989 (Box 1)
  - Free Press correspondence, 1984 - 1992 (Box 1)
  - New York Psychoanalytic Institute correspondence, 1959 - 1987 (Box 1)
  - Publication correspondence, 1983 - 1995 (Box 1)
  - Vienna/Zurich lecture correspondence, 1986 - 1987 (Box 1)
  - Vienna/Zurich lecture correspondence, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Payne Whitney Psychiatric Clinic correspondence, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Book translation correspondence, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art correspondence, 1984 (Box 1)
  - The Freudian Society, 1988 - 1989 (Box 1)
  - The Bureau of Child Guidance, 1966 (Box 1)
- Lectures, 1949 - 1995
  - Lectures/conference notes, 1949 - 1955 (Box 1)
  - Lectures/conference notes, 1956 - 1959 (Box 1)
  - Psychopathology of Adolescence/ Maladaptive Behavior, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Discussion notes on Dr. Brody’s paper, 1961 - 1962 (Box 1)
  - American Psychoanalytic Association Fall Discussion Panel, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Albert Einstein College of Medicine Child Psychiatry Lecture, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Lecture notes on adolescence, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Technical Problems of Adolescent Analysis, workshop notes, 1967 (Box 2)
  - New York Psychoanalytic Society, “Drug Use by Adolescents” lectures, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Nunberg Lecture papers, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Nunberg Lecture papers, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Nunberg Lecture papers, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Lecture and course notes on adolescence, 1968 - 1977 (Box 2)
  - Lecture and course notes on late adolescence, 1970 - 1977 (Box 2)
  - Colloquium notes, the New York Psychoanalytic Institute, 1979 - 1988 (Box 2)
  - Freudian Society Panel/lecture notes, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Freudian Society lecture and course notes, 1982 (Box 2)
  - “History of Developmental Theory” lectures/discussions, 1985 - 1987 (Box 2)
  - Postgraduate Center for Mental Health lecture, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Masculinity Conference lecture and notes, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Lecture notes, 1974 - 1986 (Box 2)
  - Lecture notes, 1977 - 1980 (Box 2)
  - Lecture notes, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Freud Lecture papers, 1988 (Box 3)
  - Freud Lecture papers, 1988 (Box 3)
  - Male Adolescent lectures, 1985 - 1988 (Box 3)
  - Adolescent lectures, Undated (Box 3)
  - Workshop notes, Undated (Box 3)
  - History of Developmental Theory lectures/discussions, Undated (Box 3)
  - Adolescent lectures by Alex Holder, Undated (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous notes, Undated (Box 3)
- Manuscripts, 1966 - 1995
  - “Son and Father” 2nd draft, 1982 (Box 3)
  - “Son and Father” with introduction, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Vienna draft “Freud and the Father Complex”, 1986 (Box 3)
  - “Freud and the Father Complex” (German), 1986 (Box 3)
  - “Freud and the Father Complex” English translation, 1986 (Box 3)
  - “Freud and the Father Complex” translation, 1986 (Box 4)
  - “Freud and the Father Complex” draft (German), Undated (Box 4)
  - Autobiographical essay copy, 1995 (Box 4)
  - Autobiographical essay first typing, Undated (Box 4)
  - Autobiographical essay “Memories”, Undated (Box 4)
  - Autobiographical essay “Vienna Years,” annotated draft, Undated (Box 4)
  - Autobiographical notes, Undated (Box 4)
  - Imago Mundi, original-copyedited, 1983 - 1993 (Box 4)
  - Imago Mundi, draft and notes, 1983 - 1993 (Box 4)
  - Imago Mundi, draft and notes, 1983 - 1993 (Box 4)
  - Imago Mundi, draft and notes, 1983 - 1993 (Box 4)
  - Imago Mundi, draft and notes, 1983 - 1993 (Box 4)
  - “Modification in the Traditional Psychoanalytic Theory of Female Adolescent Development”, 1980 (Box 4)
  - “The Contribution of Psychoanalysis to the Psychotherapy of Adolescents”, 1981 (Box 4)
  - “Maladaptive Behaviour” first draft, 1968 (Box 5)
  - “Maladaptive Behaviour” first draft, 1968 (Box 5)
  - “Maladaptive Behaviour” first draft typed, 1968 (Box 5)
  - “Maladaptive Behaviour” second draft, Undated (Box 5)
  - “Maladaptive Behaviour” second draft, Undated (Box 5)
  - “Maladaptive Behaviour” third draft, 1968 (Box 5)
  - “Maladaptive Behaviour” draft notes, Undated (Box 5)
  - “Maladaptive Behaviour” draft notes, Undated (Box 5)
  - “Maladaptive Behaviour” draft notes, Undated (Box 5)
  - “Maladaptive Behaviour,” “Family Myth” notes, Undated (Box 5)
  - Institute New York School “Maladaptive Behaviour” notes, Undated (Box 5)
  - “Le Mot Juste” An Apercu, 1995 (Box 5)
  - “Old Age”, Undated (Box 5)
  - “The Second Individuation Process of Adolescence,” edited copy, 1966 (Box 5)
  - Child Analysis Papers *removed “When Parents are Patients” to restricted materials, 1993 (Box 5)
  - “Fantasy and Reality in Psychoanalysis- Once Again” with notes, 1993 (Box 5)
  - “Romantic Love and the Adolescent Process”, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Austen Riggs Center “The Place of the Adolescent Process in the Analysis of the Adult”, 1988 (Box 6)
  - “The Place of the Adolescent Process in the Analysis of the Adult”, 1989 (Box 6)
  - “About a Psychoanalytic Theory on Adolescence” draft, 1987 (Box 6)
  - “The Relevancy of the Adolescent Process for The Psychotherapy of the Adult” draft, Undated (Box 6)
  - “The Place of Adolescence in the Psychoanalytic Theory of Neurosis” draft, 1987 (Box 6)
  - “The Place of the Adolescent Process in the Analysis of the Adult” draft, 1988 (Box 6)
  - Child Development, 1974 (Box 6)
  - The Search for Samuel B., A Play by Eugene Mahon, 1990 (Box 6)
  - The Young: A Game Show in Two Parts (German), Der Jungling Ein Schau-Spiel in 2 Bildern, Undated (Box 12)
  - Die Schenke ein aufzug, das Winzerfest ein Gedicht, Der Fischzu ein Spiel in Versen (German), Undated (Box 12)
  - Vienna Draft “Freud and the Father Complex” (German), 1986 (Box 12)
  - “The Inner World of the Adolescent”, 1985 (Box 12)
  - “The Place of the Adolescent” draft, 1987 (Box 12)
  - “Reflections on Writing the Freud Lecture”, 1988 (Box 12)
  - “Freud and the Father Complex” draft (German), Undated (Box 12)
  - “The Relevancy of the Adolescent Process for the Psychotherapy of the Adult”, 1988 (Box 12)
  - “Son and Father” 4th draft, 1982 (Box 13)
  - “The Place of the Adolescent in the Analysis of the Adult”, 1987 (Box 13)
  - “The Contribution of Psychoanalysis to the Psychotherapy of Adolescents” draft, Undated (Box 13)
  - “The Place of Adolescence in the Theory of Neurosis” 2nd draft, Undated (Box 13)
  - “About a Psychoanalytic Theory on Adolescence” draft, 1987 (Box 13)
- Marta Grone Correspondence, 1957 - 1964
  - Marta (Grone) Blos correspondence (“Pa’s Disease”), 1959 - 1960 (Box 6)
  - Marta (Grone) Blos correspondence (“Pa’s Disease”), 1960 (Box 6)
  - Marta (Grone) Blos correspondence (“Pa’s Disease”), 1960 (Box 6)
  - Marta (Grone) Blos correspondence (“Pa’s Disease”), 1960 (Box 6)
  - Marta (Grone) Blos correspondence (“Pa’s Disease”), 1960 (Box 6)
  - Marta (Grone) Blos correspondence (“Pa’s Letters”), 1958 - 1959 (Box 6)
  - Marta (Grone) Blos correspondence (“Pa’s Letters”), 1959 (Box 6)
  - Marta (Grone) Blos correspondence (“Pa’s Letters”), 1959 - 1960 (Box 6)
  - Marta (Grone) Blos correspondence (“Elsa/Pa’s Letters”), 1958 - 1959 (Box 7)
  - Marta (Grone) Blos correspondence (“Elsa/Pa’s Letters”), 1959 - 1960 (Box 7)
  - Marta (Grone) Blos correspondence, 1957 - 1959 (Box 7)
  - Marta (Grone) Blos correspondence, 1959 - 1962 (Box 7)
  - Marta (Grone) Blos correspondence, 1962 - 1964 (Box 7)
  - Marta (Grone) Blos correspondence, 1964 (Box 7)
  - Marta (Grone) Blos, Otto Grone journal reprints, Undated (Box 7)
  - Marta (Grone) Blos, miscellaneous, Undated (Box 7)
- Case Seminars, 1957 - 1963
  - RESTRICTED Child Therapy Seminar on Technique, 1953 - 1957 (Box 14)
  - RESTRICTED Child Therapy Seminar on Technique, 1961 - 1962 (Box 14)
  - Hawthorne Symposium on Female Delinquency, 1959 (Box 7)
  - Case discussions on acting out, 1962 (Box 7)
  - Case discussions miscellaneous, 1963 (Box 7)
  - RESTRICTED Miscellaneous case seminars/discussions, 1959 - 1963 (Box 14)
  - RESTRICTED New York Psychoanalytic Institute, Magruder Case Seminars, 1960 (Box 14)
  - RESTRICTED New York Psychoanalytic Institute, Magruder Case Seminars, 1960 - 1961 (Box 14)
  - RESTRICTED New York Psychoanalytic Institute, Esman Case Seminars, 1961 (Box 14)
  - RESTRICTED New York Psychoanalytic Institute, Becker Case Seminars, 1958 - 1961 (Box 14)
  - RESTRICTED New York Psychoanalytic Institute, Zavitzianos Case Seminars, 1961 - 1962 (Box 14)
  - RESTRICTED New York Psychoanalytic Institute, Zavitzianos Case Seminars, Undated (Box 14)
  - RESTRICTED New York Psychoanalytic Institute, Furer Case Seminars, 1961 (Box 14)
  - RESTRICTED Hawthorne case discussions, 1957 - 1960 (Box 14)
  - RESTRICTED Montefiore Hospital Adolescent Case Discussion, 1962 (Box 14)
- Miscellaneous, 1950 - 1993
  - The New School, 1950 (Box 8)
  - Book reviews, The Young Adolescent, 1972 (Box 8)
  - Book reviews, The Young Adolescent, 1973 (Box 8)
  - III Reunion, Mexico Pan-American Forum of Adolescence, 1975 (Box 8)
  - The American Psychoanalytic Association Psychoanalysis of the Young Adult, 1984 (Box 8)
  - Book reviews, Son and Father, 1986 (Box 8)
  - The Association of Child Psychoanalysis, 1987 (Box 8)
  - Austen Riggs Center, 1988 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1989 (Box 8)
  - Interview transcript (German), 1993 (Box 8)
  - Erik Erikson Memorial, 1994 (Box 8)
  - Book review, Rensal The Redbit, Undated (Box 8)
  - Material on adolescence, Undated (Box 8)
  - Material on adolescence, Undated (Box 8)
  - Adolescent process notes, Undated (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 8)
  - Study trip - Europe journal, 1963 (Box 9)
  - Journals I and II, 1961 - 1962 (Box 9)
  - Journals III and IV, 1962 (Box 9)
  - Journals V and VI, 1962 - 1963 (Box 9)
  - Journals VII and VIII, 1963 - 1964 (Box 10)
  - Journals X and XI, 1965 (Box 10)
  - Journal IX and Jerusalem conference notes, 1964 - 1965 (Box 10)
  - Student books (German), Meldungsbuch des Studierenden – Peter Blos, Universitat zu Wien (2 items), 1925 (Box 10)
  - III Reunion, Mexico Pan-American Forum of Adolescence Map, 1975 (Box 13)
  - Newspapers, 1991 - 1997 (Box 13)
- Reprints, 1935 - 1991
  - Miscellaneous article reprints, 1935 - 1948 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous article reprints, 1937 - 1958 (Box 7)
  - Sigmund Freud House Catalogue, 1975 (Box 7)
  - Journal Psychoanalysis Seminar Zurich, 1987 (Box 8)
  - International Journal of Psychoanalytic Psychotherapy, 1987 (Box 8)
  - Austen Riggs Center International Review Psychoanalysis Journal, 1985 - 1991 (Box 8)
  - Association for Child Psychoanalysis Newsletter, 1990 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous article reprints, Undated (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous article reprints, 1955 (Box 13)
- Photographs, 1990 - 1994
  - Photographs and negatives, 1990 (Box 11)
  - Vienna photograph album, 1994 (Box 11)
- Certificates, 1934 - 1988
  - Certificates, 1948 - 1966 (Box 8)
  - Certificates, 1934 - 1947 (Box 8)
  - Certification, 1958 - 1988 (Box 8)
  - Certificates, 1923 - 1994 (Box 13)